In the early days of Twitter, it was like a place of radical de-shaming.
عند ظهور التويتر، وقع تشبيهه كمكان مخزي بلا حياء.
People would admit shameful secrets about themselves,
يريد الناس الإفحاص عن عن الأسرار المخزية المتعلقة بهم.
and other people would say, "Oh my God, I'm exactly the same."
ويريد البعض الآخر أن يقول: "يا إلهي، أنا مثلك تماما".
Voiceless people realized that they had a voice,
أدرك الناس الذين لا صوت لهم، بأنهم أصبح لهم صوت،
and it was powerful and eloquent.
وأن صوتهم قوي وبليغ.
If a newspaper ran some racist or homophobic column,
لو نشرت صحيفة خبرا عنصرياً أو حول رهاب المثلية،
we realized we could do something about it.
أدركنا أنه يمككنا فعل شيء ما حيال ذلك.
We could get them.
يمكننا النيل منهم.
We could hit them with a weapon that we understood but they didn't --
يمككنا مواجهته بإعتماد السلاح نفهمه نحن ولكنهم لا يفهمونه--
a social media shaming.
عار وسائل التواصل الأجتماعية.
Advertisers would withdraw their advertising.
قد يقوم المعلنون بسحب إعلاناتهم.
When powerful people misused their privilege,
عندما يسيء أصحاب القوة استعمال الامتيازات التي يتمتعون بها،
we were going to get them.
كنا سنقوم بالقضاء عليهم.
This was like the democratization of justice.
هذا ما تبدو عليه ديموقراطية العدالة.
Hierarchies were being leveled out.
وقع الرفع من المراتب والدرجات.
We were going to do things better.
كنا سنقوم بأشياء أفضل.
Soon after that, a disgraced pop science writer called Jonah Lehrer --
بعد ذلك بوقت قصير، برز كاتب بغيض في مجال العلوم يدعى جونا ليرير--
he'd been caught plagiarizing and faking quotes,
تم القبض عليه بتهمة سرقة التعاليق وتزًيفها،
and he was drenched in shame and regret, he told me.
أخبرني أنه كان يشعر بالعار والندم.
And he had the opportunity
وقد أتيحت له فرصة
to publicly apologize at a foundation lunch.
للإعتذار بشكل علني في مأدبة غداء للمؤسسة.
This was going to be the most important speech of his life.
كان ذلك سيكون أهم خطاب له في حياته.
Maybe it would win him some salvation.
وربما كانت هذه فرصة لتكون وسيلة خلاصه.
He knew before he arrived
كان يعرف قبل وصوله
that the foundation was going to be live-streaming his event,
أن تلك المؤسسة ستقوم ببث هذا الحدث على المباشر،
but what he didn't know until he turned up,
ولكن لم يكن في علمه إلى أن وصل إلى المأدبة
was that they'd erected a giant screen Twitter feed right next to his head.
بأنهم قاموا بوضع شاشة ضخمة بتغريدات تويتر بجانب رأسه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Another one in a monitor screen in his eye line.
وشاشة آخرى لعرض خطابه موضوعة على مرمى بصره.
I don't think the foundation did this because they were monstrous.
ولا أعتقد أن المؤسسة قامت ذلك لانهم كانوا بهذه الفظاعة.
I think they were clueless: I think this was a unique moment
أعتقد أنه لم تكن لهم معرفة بذلك: أعتقد أنها كانت لحظة فريدة
when the beautiful naivety of Twitter
حين تقوم السذاجة البريئة لتويتر
was hitting the increasingly horrific reality.
بضرب الحقيقة المروعة على نحو متزايد.
And here were some of the Tweets that were cascading into his eye line,
وكانت بعض التغريدات تتعاقب أمام ناظريه،
as he was trying to apologize:
أثناء محاولته لتقديم الإعتذار:
"Jonah Lehrer, boring us into forgiving him."
"جونا ليرر، يسبب لنا الملل ليجعلنا نسامحه ."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And, "Jonah Lehrer has not proven that he is capable of feeling shame."
وأيضا " لم يثبت لنا جونا ليرر أنه يشعر بالعار."
That one must have been written by the best psychiatrist ever,
لا ان كاتب هذا التعليق أفضل طبيب نفسي على الإطلاق
to know that about such a tiny figure behind a lectern.
يكون على دراية بهذا الأمر الدقيق لشخص خلف المنبر.
And, "Jonah Lehrer is just a frigging sociopath."
وأيضا " جون ليرر ليس إلا معتل إجتماعي غريب الأطوار."
That last word is a very human thing to do, to dehumanize the people we hurt.
تعتبر الكلمة الأخيرة شيئا إنسانيا نقوم به لإذلال من نقوم بإيذائهم.
It's because we want to destroy people but not feel bad about it.
لأننا نريد تدمير الناس ولكن لا نشعر بالأسف حيال ذلك.
Imagine if this was an actual court,
لنتخيل أنّ هذه كانت محكمة حقيقية،
and the accused was in the dark, begging for another chance,
والمتهم موجود في الظلام يتوسل للحصول على فرصة آخرى،
and the jury was yelling out,
وكانت هيئة المحلفين تصرخ بأعلى صوتها
"Bored! Sociopath!"
" ممل! معتل اجتماعيا !"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know, when we watch courtroom dramas, we tend to identify
أتدرون؟ عندما نشاهد قاعة المحكمة في الدراما، نميل الى التشبّه
with the kindhearted defense attorney,
بطيبة قلب محامي الدفاع،
but give us the power, and we become like hanging judges.
ولكن هذا يعطينا القوة ويجعلنا نشبه القضاة.
Power shifts fast.
تتحول السلطة بطريقة سريعة.
We were getting Jonah because he was perceived to have misused his privilege,
أمسكنا بجونا لأننا أدركنا أنه أساء استخدام الامتيازات التي لديه
but Jonah was on the floor then, and we were still kicking,
ولكن كان جونا على الأرض ونحن ننهال عليه بالركل،
and congratulating ourselves for punching up.
وكنا نهنئ أنفسنا لمعاقبته.
And it began to feel weird and empty when there wasn't a powerful person
وبدأ شعور بالغرابة والفراغ يتسلل عندما لم يكن يوجد شخص ذا نفوذ
who had misused their privilege that we could get.
والذي أساء استخدام الامتيازات التي كان يمكننا الحصول عليها.
A day without a shaming began to feel like a day
أصبح يوم بدون عار يشبه يوما
picking fingernails and treading water.
نقوم فيه بتقليم الأظافر والبقاء داخل الماء.
Let me tell you a story.
دعني أروي لكم قصة.
It's about a woman called Justine Sacco.
تتعلق هذه القصة بامرأة تدعى جوستين ساككو.
She was a PR woman from New York with 170 Twitter followers,
كانت تعمل في العلاقات العامة بنيويورك، كان لديها 170 متابع على تويتر،
and she'd Tweet little acerbic jokes to them,
حيث كانت تقوم بكتابة بعض النكات اللاذعة لهم على تويتر،
like this one on a plane from New York to London:
مثل هذه النكتة حول واحد على متن طائرة متجهة من نيويورك نحو لندن:
[Weird German Dude: You're in first class. It's 2014. Get some deodorant."
[رجل ألماني غريب الأطوار: أنت في الدرجة الأولى وفي 2014. اشتري مزيلا للعرق."
-Inner monologue as inhale BO. Thank god for pharmaceuticals.]
-مناجاة داخلية تشبه استنشاق فيروس التهاب القصيبات. الحمد لله على الأدوية.]
So Justine chuckled to herself, and pressed send, and got no replies,
ضحكت جوستين على نفسها، وقامت بالنقرعلى إرسال ولم تحصل على أي رد.
and felt that sad feeling that we all feel
وانتابها ذاك الإحساس بالحزن الذي نشعر به
when the Internet doesn't congratulate us for being funny.
عندما لا يطري علينا أحد ويهنئنا على خفة ظلنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Black silence when the Internet doesn't talk back.
يسود الانترنت صمت رهيب عندما لا تتحدث مرة آخرى.
And then she got to Heathrow, and she had a little time to spare
وبعد ذلك وصلت لمطار هيثرو وكان لديها بعض الوقت
before her final leg, so she thought up another funny little acerbic joke:
قبل أن تصل لوجهتها الأخيرة، فقامت بإلقاء مزحة آخرى لاذعة:
[Going to Africa. Hope I don't get AIDS. Just kidding. I'm white!]
[سأذهب إلى أفريقيا. أرجو أن لا أصاب بالإيدز. أمزح. أنا بيضاء البشرة!]
And she chuckled to herself, pressed send, got on the plane, got no replies,
وضحكت على نفسها وضغطت على إرسال، ثم صعدت إلى الطائرة ولم تحصل على رد،
turned off her phone, fell asleep,
أغلقت هاتفها واستغرقت في النوم،
woke up 11 hours later,
استيقظت بعد 11 ساعة،
turned on her phone while the plane was taxiing on the runway,
قامت بتشغيل هاتفها أثناء اتجاه الطائرة نحو المدرج المخصص لها.
and straightaway there was a message from somebody
وفورا كانت توجد رسالة من شخص
that she hadn't spoken to since high school,
لم تتحدث معه منذ المدرسة الثانوية،
that said, "I am so sorry to see what's happening to you."
والذي قال في رسالته:" أنا أسف لما يحدث لك."
And then another message from a best friend,
وثم ذلك رسالة آخرى من صديقتها المقربة،
"You need to call me right now.
" يجب أن تتصلي بي حالا،
You are the worldwide number one trending topic on Twitter."
أصبحت موضوع البحث رقم واحد في العالم على تويتر."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What had happened is that one of her 170 followers had sent the Tweet
ما حدث هو أن واحدا من 170متابعا قام بإرسال التغريدة
to a Gawker journalist, and he retweeted it to his 15,000 followers:
لصحفي بجريدة "الأخرق" والذي قام بإعادة نشرها لمتابعيه الذي يبلغ عددهم 15.000
[And now, a funny holiday joke from IAC's PR boss]
[والآن، مزحة نهاية الأسبوع تأتيكم من طرف مديرة العلاقات العامة]
And then it was like a bolt of lightning.
وكان ذلك كالصاعقة.
A few weeks later, I talked to the Gawker journalist.
بعد مرور أسابيع قليلة، اتصلت بالصحفي.
I emailed him and asked him how it felt, and he said, "It felt delicious."
أرسلت له بريدا إلكترونيا سألته فيه عن شعوره فأجابني بأنه يشعر بالمتعة.
And then he said, "But I'm sure she's fine."
ثم أخبرني أنه متأكد من أنها بخير.
But she wasn't fine, because while she slept,
لكنها فعلا لم تكن بخير، لأنها أثناء نومها
Twitter took control of her life and dismantled it piece by piece.
تولى تويتر السيطرة على حياتها وبدأ بتفكيكها إلى قطع.
First there were the philanthropists:
أولا كان هناك واحد من فاعلي الخير قام بكتابة:
[If @JustineSacco's unfortunate words ... bother you,
[ إذا أزعجتك كلمات جوستين ساككو..
join me in supporting @CARE's work in Africa.]
انضم إلي وشاركني في دعم منظمة @CARE الناشطة بإفريقيا.]
[In light of ... disgusting, racist tweet, I'm donating to @care today]
[ على الضوء.. التغريدة المثيرة للاشمئزاز والعنصرية، فأنني أتبرع اليوم ل@care ]
Then came the beyond horrified:
ثم ظهرت هذه التغريدة المروعة:
[... no words for that horribly disgusting racist as fuck tweet from Justine Sacco.
[ ...لا يوجد رد لهذه الكلمات الفظيعة والعنصرية التي كتبتها جوستين ساككو.
I am beyond horrified.]
انني أكثر من مذعور.]
Was anybody on Twitter that night? A few of you.
هل يوجد من كان على تويتر تلك الليلة؟ القليل منكم
Did Justine's joke overwhelm your Twitter feed the way it did mine?
هل سحقت نكات جاستين التغريدات كما تفعل الألغام؟
It did mine, and I thought what everybody thought that night,
هذا حدث معي، وفكرت بما فكر به الجميع تلك الليلة،
which was, "Wow, somebody's screwed!
وهو أن شخص ما انتهى أمره
Somebody's life is about to get terrible!"
وأن حياة أحدهم على وشك الانهيار.
And I sat up in my bed,
جلست على سريري،
and I put the pillow behind my head,
ووضعت وسادة خلف رأسي،
and then I thought, I'm not entirely sure that joke was intended to be racist.
وأستغرقت في التفكير، لست متأكد أن القصد من هذه المزحة هو العنصرية.
Maybe instead of gleefully flaunting her privilege,
ربما بدلا من التباهي ببهجة بامتيازاتها
she was mocking the gleeful flaunting of privilege.
كانت تسخر من أولئك الذين يتباهون بامتيازاتهم.
There's a comedy tradition of this,
توجد كوميديا تقليدية ،
like South Park or Colbert or Randy Newman.
مثل ساوث بارك وكولبير وراندي نيومان.
Maybe Justine Sacco's crime was not being as good at it as Randy Newman.
ربما ذنب جوستين ساككو هو أنها لم تكن جيدة مثل راندي نيومان.
In fact, when I met Justine a couple of weeks later in a bar,
في الحقيقة، عند قابلت جوستين في حانة بعد أسابيع قليلة من الحادثة
she was just crushed,
كانت محطمة نفسيا،
and I asked her to explain the joke,
وطلبت منها أن تشرح لي المزحة،
and she said, "Living in America puts us in a bit of a bubble
فأخبرتني أن الحياة في أمريكا تجعل الفرد يعيش كأنه في فقاعة
when it comes to what is going on in the Third World.
عندما يتعلق الأمر بما يحدث في العالم الثالث.
I was making of fun of that bubble."
وأنها كانت تسخر من تلك الفقاعة.
You know, another woman on Twitter that night, a New Statesman writer Helen Lewis,
هل تعلمون، كانت توجد امرأة آخرى تلك الليلة، كاتبة سياسية جديدة: هيلين لويس.
she reviewed my book on public shaming and wrote that she Tweeted that night,
قامت بمراجعة كتابي حول الفضح العلني، إذ كتبت أنها قامت بنشر تغريدة تلك الليلة
"I'm not sure that her joke was intended to be racist,"
" لست متأكدة من أن معنى المزحة كان عنصريا"
and she said straightaway she got a fury of Tweets saying,
وأخبرتني أنها على الفور حصلت على تغريدات تقول:
"Well, you're just a privileged bitch, too."
" حسنا، أنت لست إلا عاهرة ذات امتيازات، أيضا."
And so to her shame, she wrote,
ولذك كتبت بسبب الخجل الذي أحست به
she shut up and watched as Justine's life got torn apart.
بأنها أغلقت فمها وبقيت تشاهد حياة جوستين تنهار.
It started to get darker:
بدأ الأمر يزداد سوءا:
[Everyone go report this cunt @JustineSacco]
[ ليقم الجميع بالإبلاغ عن هذا الحساب JustineSacco@]
Then came the calls for her to be fired.
ثم تلقت اتصالا يخبرها بأنه تم فصلها من العمل.
[Good luck with the job hunt in the new year. #GettingFired]
[حظا سعيدا في البحث عن وظيفة في العام الجديد. GettingFired# ]
Thousands of people around the world
قرر الآلاف من جميع أنحاء العالم
decided it was their duty to get her fired.
بأنه من واجبهم جعلها تطرد من العمل.
[@JustineSacco last tweet of your career. #SorryNotSorry
[ جوستين ساككو التغريدة الأخيرة من حياتك المهنية. SorryNotSorry#
Corporations got involved, hoping to sell their products
تدخلت المنظمات، أرجو أن تبيع منتجاتها،
on the back of Justine's annihilation:
على خلفية تدمير جوستين:
[Next time you plan to tweet something stupid before you take off,
[في المرة القادمة عندما تخططين لكتابة تغريدة حول شيء غبي قبل الإقلاع
make sure you are getting on a @Gogo flight!]
تأكدي من أنك على متن رحلة Gogo@!]
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
A lot of companies were making good money that night.
جنت الكثير من الشركات مالا كثيرا في تلك الليلة.
You know, Justine's name was normally Googled 40 times a month.
أتعلمون، كان يقع البحث عن اسم جوستين 40 مرة في الشهر.
That month, between December the 20th and the end of December,
في ذاك الشهر، من 20 ديسمبر إلى آخر الشهر
her name was Googled 1,220,000 times.
تم البحث عن اسمها 1.220.00 مرة.
And one Internet economist told me that that meant that Google made
كما أخبرني خبير إقتصادي للانترنت بأن جوجل جنى
somewhere between 120,000 dollars and 468,000 dollars
ما بين 120.000 دولار و468.000 دولار
from Justine's annihilation, whereas those of us doing the actual shaming --
من محاولة تدمير جوستين، في حين من يكتب الفضح
we got nothing.
لم نصل لشيء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We were like unpaid shaming interns for Google.
كنا كالمتدربين على الفضح لجوجل بدون أجر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then came the trolls:
ومن ثم ظهر المتصيدون:
[I'm actually kind of hoping Justine Sacco gets aids? lol]
[أنا في الواقع أمل أن تصاب جوستين بمرض الايدز؟ لول]
Somebody else on that wrote,
شخص ما كتب،
"Somebody HIV-positive should rape this bitch and then we'll find out
" يجب أن يعتدي على هذه السافلة شخص حامل لفيروس الإيدز وسنكتشف
if her skin color protects her from AIDS."
إذا استطاع لون بشرتها حمايتها من الايدز."
And that person got a free pass.
فحصل هذا الشخص على تشيرة مرور مجانية.
Nobody went after that person.
لم يقم أي أحد بملاحقته.
We were all so excited about destroying Justine,
لقد كنا كلنا متحمسين بتدمير جوستين،
and our shaming brains are so simple-minded,
ويعتبر تفكيرنا المحرج بسيطا.
that we couldn't also handle destroying somebody
حيث أننا لم نستطع التعامل مع فكرة تدمير حياة شخص
who was inappropriately destroying Justine.
الذي كان يدمر حياة جوستين على نحو غير لائق.
Justine was really uniting a lot of disparate groups that night,
قامت جوستين تلك الليلة بتوحيد العديد من المجموعات،
from philanthropists to "rape the bitch."
من فاعل الخير إلى "إغتصاب السافلة"
[@JustineSacco I hope you get fired! You demented bitch...
[Jجوستين سلككو أرجو أن يقع طردك من عملك! أيتها الكلبة المجنونة ...
Just let the world know you're planning to ride bare back while in Africa.]
أعلمي الجميع أنك تخططن الذهاب إلى أفربقيا عارية الظهر.]
Women always have it worse than men.
فضح المرأة دائما أسوأ من الرجال.
When a man gets shamed, it's, "I'm going to get you fired."
عندما يتم ذم الرجل فأنه يقال " سأجعلك تطرد من عملك."
When a woman gets shamed, it's,
وعندما يتم ذم المرأة فإنه يكون،
"I'm going to get you fired and raped and cut out your uterus."
" سأجعلك تطردين من عملك ويقع اغتصابك وقطع رحمك"
And then Justine's employers got involved:
وعندها تدخل العاملون مع جوستين:
[IAC on @JustineSacco tweet: This is an outrageous, offensive comment.
[ تغريدة الشركة على حساب جوستين: هذا تعليق مهين وعدواني.
Employee in question currently unreachable on an intl flight.]
لا يمكن الاتصال بالموظفة المقصودة من على متن الطائرة.]
And that's when the anger turned to excitement:
وعند ذلك تحول الغضب إلى إثارة:
[All I want for Christmas is to see @JustineSacco's face when her plane lands
[كل ما أريده لعيد الميلاد هو أن أرى وجه JustineSacco @ بعد أن تحط طائرتها
and she checks her inbox/voicemail. #fired]
وتتفقد رسائلها وبريدها الصوتي. #مطرودة. ]
[Oh man, @justinesacco is going to have the most painful
[ ستتعرض جوستين ساككو لأكثر إعادة فتح هاتف
phone-turning-on moment ever when her plane lands.]
ألما من أي وقت مضى عندما تحط الطائرة.]
[We are about to watch this @JustineSacco bitch get fired. In REAL time.
[ نحن على وشك رؤية جوستين تطرد فعليا،
Before she even KNOWS she's getting fired.]
حتى قبل أن تدرك بأنها طردت.]
What we had was a delightful narrative arc.
ما كان لدينا هو جزء من قصة مبهجة.
We knew something that Justine didn't.
نحن نعرف شيئا لم تكن جوستين على علم به.
Can you think of anything less judicial than this?
هل يمكنك التفكير في شيء أقل تمييزا من هذا؟
Justine was asleep on a plane and unable to explain herself,
كانت جوستين نائمة على متن الطائرة وغير قادرة على شرح موقفها،
and her inability was a huge part of the hilarity.
وكان عجزها جزءا كبيرا من المرح.
On Twitter that night, we were like toddlers crawling towards a gun.
في تلك الليلة على تويتر، كنا كالصغار نزحف باتجاه السلاح.
Somebody worked out exactly which plane she was on, so they linked
شخص ما كان يعمل على متن الطائرة التي تقلها، لذلك قام بنشر
to a flight tracker website.
على موقع خاص بتعقب الرحلات الجوية
[British Airways Flight 43 On-time - arrives in 1 hour 34 minutes]
[الرحلة 43 لشركة الخطوط البريطانية في وقتها - تصل بعد 1 ساعة و34 دقيقة]
A hashtag began trending worldwide:
وبدأت وسم المربع ينهال من كل أنحاء العالم:
# hasJustineLandedYet?
# هل هبطت طائرة جوستين بعد؟
[It is kinda wild to see someone self-destruct
[ يبدو غريبا أن ترى شخصا يدمر نفسه
without them even being aware of it. #hasJustineLandedYet]
بدون أن يكون على دراية بذلك. # هل هبطت طائرة جوستين بعد؟]
[Seriously. I just want to go home to go to bed, but everyone at the bar
[ جديا، أريد فقط أن أعود للمنزل وأخلد للنوم، ولكن الجميع في الحانة،
is SO into #HasJustineLandedYet. Can't look away. Can't leave.]
منغمسون في # هل هبطت طائرة جوستين بعد؟ لا أستطيع ابعاد نظري والرحيل.]
[#HasJustineLandedYet may be the best thing to happen to my Friday night.]
[ قد يكون # هل هبطت طائرة جوستين بعد؟ أفضل شيء حدث لي ليلة الجمعة. ]
[Is no one in Cape Town going to the airport to tweet her arrival?
[ هل يوجد أحد من كيب تاون ذاهب الى المطار ليغرّد لنا وصولها؟
Come on, twitter! I'd like pictures]
هيا، تويتر! أريد رؤية صور.]
And guess what? Yes there was.
وخمن ماذا؟ نعم كان هناك صور.
[@JustineSacco HAS in fact landed at Cape Town international.
[ حلت جوستين ساككو بمطار كاب تاون الدولي.
And if you want to know what it looks like to discover
اذا أردت تعرف كيف تبدو عندما تكتشف
that you've just been torn to shreds because of a misconstrued liberal joke,
أنه وقع تمزيقك لأشلاء بسسب مزحة أُسيء فهمها،
not by trolls, but by nice people like us,
ليس من طرف المتصييدين بل أشخاص مثلنا.
this is what it looks like:
هذا ما يبدو عليه الوضع:
[... She's decided to wear sunnies as a disguise.]
[... قررت ارتداء نظارات شمسية كتمويه.]
So why did we do it?
بالتالي لماذا قمنا بذلك؟
I think some people were genuinely upset,
أعتقد أن بعض الأشخاص كانوا يشعرون حقا بالانزعاج،
but I think for other people,
لكن أعتقد أن الآخرين،
it's because Twitter is basically a mutual approval machine.
يعتبرون تويتر أساسا آلة موافقة مشتركة.
We surround ourselves with people who feel the same way we do,
حيث أننا نحيط أنفسنا بأشخاص نشعر بأنهم مثلنا،
and we approve each other,
ونوافق بعضنا البعض،
and that's a really good feeling.
وذلك حقا شعور جيد.
And if somebody gets in the way, we screen them out.
وإذا اعترض أحد طريقنا، نقوم بحجبه وإقصائه.
And do you know what that's the opposite of?
هل تعرف ما عكس ذلك؟
It's the opposite of democracy.
انه عكس الديمقراطية.
We wanted to show that we cared about people dying of AIDS in Africa.
أردنا أن نظهر أننا نهتم بمشكلة موت الناس في افريقيا بسبب الايدز.
Our desire to be seen to be compassionate is what led us to commit
رغبتنا في أن نبدو رؤوفين هو ما دفعنا لإرتكاب
this profoundly un-compassionate act.
هذه الأفعال القاسية.
As Meghan O'Gieblyn wrote in the Boston Review,
كما كتبت ميغان أوغيلين في مجلة بوسطن،
"This isn't social justice. It's a cathartic alternative."
" هذه ليست العدالة الاجتماعي، بل انها البديل المسهل."
For the past three years,
للسنوات الثلاث الماضية،
I've been going around the world meeting people like Justine Sacco --
قمت بجولة حول أنحاء العالم وقابلت أشخاصا مثل جوستين ساككو--
and believe me, there's a lot of people like Justine Sacco.
وصدقني عندما أخبرك بأنه يوجد الكثير مثل جوستين ساككو.
There's more every day.
ويزيد العدد كل يوم.
And we want to think they're fine, but they're not fine.
ونريد أن نقتنع بأنهم بخير، ولكن هذا غير صحيح.
The people I met were mangled.
قابلت أشخاص كانوا مشوهين.
They talked to me about depression,
تحدثوا معي حول الاكتئاب،
and anxiety and insomnia and suicidal thoughts.
والقلق والأرق والأفكار الانتحارية.
One woman I talked to, who also told a joke that landed badly,
تحدثت الى امرأة، والتي قامت بالقاء مزحة عادت عليها سلبيا.
she stayed home for a year and a half.
بقيت في منزلها لمدة سنة ونصف.
Before that, she worked with adults with learning difficulties,
عملت في الماضي مع الكبار الذين يعانون صعوبة في التعلم،
and was apparently really good at her job.
وكانت جيدة في عملها على ما يبدو.
Justine was fired, of course, because social media demanded it.
بالطبع، تم طرد جوستين من عملها حسب طلب مواقع التواصل الاجتماعي.
But it was worse than that.
ولكن كان الأمر أسوأ من ذلك.
She was losing herself.
لقد كانت تخسر نفسها.
She was waking up in the middle of the night, forgetting who she was.
كانت تستيقظ في وسط الليل، لا تتذكر من هي.
She was got because she was perceived to have misused her privilege.
حدث لها هذا لأنهم لاحظوا انها أساءت استخدام امتيازاتها.
And of course, that's a much better thing to get people for than the things
وبطبيعة الحال، هذا أفضل بكثير لمعاقبة الناس بدلا من ذلك الشيء
we used to get people for, like having children out of wedlock.
الذي اعتدناه مثل انجاب أطفال خارج إطار الزواج.
But the phrase "misuse of privilege" is becoming a free pass
ولكن أصبحت عبارة " سوء استخدام الامتياز" تأشيرة عبور مجانية
to tear apart pretty much anybody we choose to.
لهدم حياة أي شخص نختاره.
It's becoming a devalued term,
لقد أصبح مصطلح منحط القيمة،
and it's making us lose our capacity for empathy
وجعنا نفقد قدرتنا على ابراز التعاطف
and for distinguishing between serious and unserious transgressions.
وعلى التفرقة بين الانتهاكات الخطيرة وغير الخطيرة.
Justine had 170 Twitter followers, and so to make it work,
كان لجوستين 170 متابعا على تويتر، لذلك و لانجاح الأمر
she had to be fictionalized.
كان يجب أن تطلق العنان للمخيله.
Word got around that she was the daughter the mining billionaire Desmond Sacco.
انتشرت إشاعة تقول بأنها ابنة ملياردير التعدين ديزموند ساككو.
[Let us not be fooled by #JustineSacco her father is a SA mining billionaire.
[دعونا لا ننخدع #JustineSacco ، والدها هو ملياردير مالك شركات التعدين.
She's not sorry. And neither is her father.]
هي لا تشعر بالأسف. ولا والدها.]
I thought that was true about Justine,
اعتقدت أن كل ما يتعلق بها صحيح.
until I met her at a bar, and I asked her about her billionaire father,
إلى أن قابلتها في الحانة وسألتها حول والدها الملياردير،
and she said, "My father sells carpets."
فأجابتني بأن والدها بائع زرابي.
And I think back on the early days of Twitter,
وأعتقد أنه في الماضي، عند انتشار تويتر
when people would admit shameful secrets about themselves,
عندما يبوح الناس بأسرارهم المخزية
and other people would say, "Oh my God, I'm exactly the same."
ويعترف آخرون بأن هذا ينطبق عليهم أيضا.
These days, the hunt is on for people's shameful secrets.
في هذه الأيام، أصبح يوجد مطاردة لأسرار الناس المخزية.
You can lead a good, ethical life,
يمكنك أن تعيش حياة جيدة وأخلاقية،
but some bad phraseology in a Tweet can overwhelm it all,
ولكن يمكن لبعض العبارات السيئة على تويتر أن تطغى على كل شيء،
become a clue to your secret inner evil.
وتصبح مفتاحا لأسرارك الشريرة والداخلية.
Maybe there's two types of people in the world:
ربما يوجد نوعان من الأشخاص في العالم:
those people who favor humans over ideology,
أولئك الذين يفضلون الانسانية على الايديولوجية
and those people who favor ideology over humans.
وأولئك الذين يفضلون الايديولوجية على الانسانية.
I favor humans over ideology,
أنا أفضل الانسانية على الايديولوجية،
but right now, the ideologues are winning,
ولكن في الوقت الحالي، الايديولوجيات تفوز،
and they're creating a stage for constant artificial high dramas
وهم بصدد انشاء مرحلة للدراما اصطناعية متواصلة
where everybody's either a magnificent hero
حيث يكون الجميع إما البطل الرائع
or a sickening villain,
أو الشرير المقزز.
even though we know that's not true about our fellow humans.
على الرغم من اننا نعلم أن هذا لا ينطبق على متابعين البشر.
What's true is that we are clever and stupid;
الصحيح هو أننا أذكياء وأغبياء.
what's true is that we're grey areas.
الصحيح هو أننا كاللون الرمادي.
The great thing about social media was how it gave a voice
إن الشيء العظيم في وسائل التواصل الاجتماعية هو أنها تعطي صوتا
to voiceless people,
للأشخاص الذين لا صوت لهم،
but we're now creating a surveillance society,
ولككنا الآن بصدد انشاء مجتمع للمراقبة
where the smartest way to survive is to go back to being voiceless.
حيث أن أفضل طريقة للعيش هو أن تعود لتصبح بدون حق للتعبير.
Let's not do that.
دعونا لا نقوم بهذا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Thank you, Jon.
برونو جيوساني: شكرا لك، جون
Jon Ronson: Thanks, Bruno.
جون رونسون: شكرا، برونو.
BG: Don't go away.
برونو: لا تبتعد
What strikes me about Justine's story
ما صدمني في قصة جوستين،
is also the fact that if you Google her name today,
هو أنه في الحقيقة إذا قمت بالبحث عن اسمها اليوم،
this story covers the first 100 pages of Google results --
ستغطي هذه القصة حوالي مئة صفحة من صفحة النتائج
there is nothing else about her.
لا يوجد شيء آخر حولها.
In your book, you mention another story
ذكرت في كتابك قصة آخرى
of another victim who actually got taken on by a reputation management firm,
لضحية آخرى والتي في الحقيقة كانت ضحية شركة ذات سمعة،
and by creating blogs and posting nice, innocuous stories about her love for cats
وبإنشاء مدونة ووضع صور لطيفة وقصص ايجابية حول حبها للقطط
and holidays and stuff, managed to get the story
والأعياد وأشياء آخرى، تمكنوا من جمع قصص
off the first couple pages of Google results, but it didn't last long.
من الصفحات الآولى القليلة من جوجل ولكنها لم تبقى لمدة طويلة.
A couple of weeks later, they started creeping back up to the top result.
بعد بضعة أسابيع، بدأوا في مراجعة أفضل النتائج الماضية
Is this a totally lost battle?
هل خسروا هذه المعركة تماما؟
Jon Ronson: You know, I think the very best thing we can do,
جون: هل تعلم؟ أعتقد أن أفضل شيء يمكننا القيام به
if you see a kind of unfair or an ambiguous shaming,
إذا اعترضك نوعا ما ظلم أو وقاحة مبهمة
is to speak up, because I think the worst thing that happened to Justine
هو التكلم لأنني أعتقد أن أسوأ شيء حدث لجوستين
was that nobody supported her -- like, everyone was against her,
هو عدم وجود شخص لتأييدها-- وكأن الجميع كانوا ضدها.
and that is profoundly traumatizing,
يعتبر هذا صدمة عميقة،
to be told by tens of thousands of people that you need to get out.
عندما يخبرك عشرات الآلاف من الأشخاص أنك يجب أن تغادر.
But if a shaming happens and there's a babble of voices, like in a democracy,
ولكن ان حدث ويوجد الكثير من الأصوات، مثلما يوجد في الديمقراطية،
where people are discussing it, I think that's much less damaging.
حيث يتحاور الناس حوله، فأنني أعتقد أنه أقل ضررا.
So I think that's the way forward,
لذلك أعتقد أن هذا هو الطريق
but it's hard, because if you do stand up for somebody,
ولكنه صعب، إذا وقفت للدفاع عن أحدهم.
it's incredibly unpleasant.
فهو مزعج للغاية.
BG: So let's talk about your experience,
برونو: إذن لنتحدث عن تجربتك،
because you stood up by writing this book.
لأنك تكلمت بكتابتك لهذا الكتاب.
By the way, it's mandatory reading for everybody, okay?
بالمناسبة، تعتبر القراءة للجميع أمرا إلزاميا، فهمت؟
You stood up because the book actually puts the spotlight on shamers.
أنت كنت من المعارضين لأن كتابك في الحقيقة يسلط الضوء عليهم.
And I assume you didn't only have friendly reactions on Twitter.
كما أفترض أنك لم تحصل على ردود ودية على تويتر.
JR: It didn't go down that well with some people.
جون: لم تجري الأمور بشكل جيد مع بعضهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, you don't want to just concentrate --
ما أريد قوله، هو أنني لا أريد التركيز--
because lots of people understood, and were really nice about the book.
لأن الكثير من الناس يفهم وكان انطباعهم جيد فيما يتعلق بالكتاب.
But yeah, for 30 years I've been writing stories about abuses of power,
ولكن نعم، طوال 30 سنة، كنت أكتب قصصا حول سوء استعمال القوة،
and when I say the powerful people over there in the military,
وعندما أقول ذوي النفوذ موجودون هناك في الجيش
or in the pharmaceutical industry, everybody applauds me.
أو في مجال صناعة الأدوية، فإن الجميع يهتف لي.
As soon as I say, "We are the powerful people abusing our power now,"
ما ان أقول: "إننا الأقوياء الذين يسيؤون استخدام قوتهم الآن."
I get people saying, "Well you must be a racist too."
ويوجد من يقول: " حسنا، أنت عنصري أيضا."
BG: So the other night -- yesterday -- we were at dinner,
برونو: في تلك الليلة-- البارحة -- كنا نتناول العشاء،
and there were two discussions going on.
وكان يوجد موضوعين كنا بصدد نقاشه.
On one side you were talking with people around the table --
في الطرف الأول كنت تتحدث مع أشخاص حول الطاولة--
and that was a nice, constructive discussion.
والذي كان حوارا جيدا وبناءَ.
On the other, every time you turned to your phone,
وفي الطرف الآخر، كلما ألقيت نظرة على هاتفك
there is this deluge of insults.
تجد وابلا من الشتائم.
JR: Yeah. This happened last night. We had like a TED dinner last night.
جون: نعم، هذا ما حدث ليلة البارحة. كنا في عشاء TED ليلة البارحة.
We were chatting and it was lovely and nice, and I decided to check Twitter.
كنا نتجاذب أطراف الحديث وكان لطيفا وجيدا، فقررت إلقاء نظرة على تويتر.
Somebody said, "You are a white supremacist."
حيث كتب لي شخص: "أنت شخص أبيض عنصري."
And then I went back and had a nice conversation with somebody,
وبعد ذلك عدت وأجريت حوارا لطيفا مع أحدهم.
and then I went back to Twitter,
ثم رجعت إلى تويتر مرة اخرى،
somebody said my very existence made the world a worse place.
كتب أحدهم أن وجودي جعل من العالم مكانا سيئا.
My friend Adam Curtis says
قال صديقي آدم كورتيس
that maybe the Internet is like a John Carpenter movie from the 1980s,
أن الانترنت ربما يشبه فيلم جون كاربنتر من الثمانينات،
when eventually everyone will start screaming at each other
عندما يبدأ الجميع في نهاية المطاف بالصراخ على بعضهم البعض،
and shooting each other, and then eventually everybody
وإطلاق النار على بعضهم البعض ثم وفي نهاية الأمر
would flee to somewhere safer,
سيهرب الجميع إلى مكان آمن.
and I'm starting to think of that as a really nice option.
كما أنني بدأت أفكر في أن هذا خيار جيد حقا.
BG: Jon, thank you. JR: Thank you, Bruno.
برونو: جون، شكرا لك. جون: شكرا لك، برونو.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)